Abby Rockefeller Mauzé papers FA337
Rockefeller Archive Center
Abby Rockefeller Mauzé papers
1905-1975
Rockefeller Archive Center
Mauze, Abby Rockefeller (1903-1976)
Rockefeller, John D., Jr. (John Davison) (1874-1960)
Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich (1874-1948)
FA337
3.04 Cubic Feet
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Biographical/Historical note
Abby Rockefeller Mauzé (November 9, 1903-May 27, 1976) was born Abby Rockefeller in New York City, the first child and only daughter of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (1874-1960) and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller (1874-1948). She soon became known as "Babs" to family and friends to differentiate her from her mother. She attended Brearley School and Miss Chapin's School, both located in New York City.
Along with her five brothers--John 3rd, Nelson, Laurance, Winthrop, and David--Babs continued the Rockefeller family's philanthropic tradition established by her father and grandfather. In contrast to her brothers, who became public figures, she conducted her philanthropic activities quietly. She was a member of the Board of Trustees of the Rockefeller Brothers Fund; an advisory member of the Board of Trustees of Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center (a chief benefactor of the Center along with her brother Laurance, she received its Medal of Appreciation in 1965); and an honorary trustee of the Rockefeller Family Fund.
She also was a benefactor of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the YWCA, New York Hospital, the Museum of Modern of Art (of which her mother was a founder, and in whose development her brothers Nelson and David played major roles), the New York Zoological Society (which also was a major interest of her brother Laurance), and the Asia Society (in whose development her brother John also played a major role).
In 1968 Babs created the Greenacre Foundation, of which she was president, to maintain and operate one or more parks in New York for the benefit of the public. In 1971, she established Greenacre Park, a small vest-pocket park and waterfall on 51st Street in Manhattan, to provide New Yorkers "some moments of serenity in this busy world." Laurance Rockefeller, a trustee of the Foundation, also helped to create the park.
Babs Rockefeller was married three times. On May 14, 1925, she married David M. Milton, a lawyer and investment banker. The Miltons had two children: Abby (who married George Dorr O'Neill) and Marilyn (who married William Kelly Simpson). The Miltons were divorced in 1943. In 1946, Babs married Dr. Irving H. Pardee, a neurologist, who died in 1949. On April 23, 1953, she married Jean Mauzé, senior vice president of United States Trust Company. He died in 1974. Mrs. Mauzé died May 27, 1976, at her Manhattan apartment on Beekman Place.
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged in seven series and one subseries:
Series 1 - Family.Series 2 - Finances.Series 3 - Real Estate. Series 4 - Subject Files.Series 5 - Children and Grandchildren. Series 6 - Personal Diaries.Series 7 - Audiovisual materials. Abby Rockefeller Mauze family photographs, Subseries 1005A.
Scope and Contents note
This collection documents the private life and personal activities, largely philanthropic, of Abby Rockefeller Mauzé (1903-1976). The bulk of the material contained in the collection dates from before 1960.
This small collection will likely have significance for scholars working in women's studies who can gain a sense of the work of an intensely private philanthropist whose family was otherwise dominated by powerful men.
Additional materials of note are the folders of correspondence with her father, mother, and brothers. Interactions with her daughters and their spouses are also noteworthy.
Related Archival Materials note
Related material may be found in the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, in several series: Cultural Interests, and Medical Interests. Additional archival material documenting the life and work of Abby Mauzé may be found in Abby Aldrich Rockefeller papers, and the David Rockefeller papers, Record Group 3 - Rockefeller Family and Associates General Files. The materials in Record Group 3 discuss Mrs. Mauzé's Greenacre Foundation and Greenacre Park, as well as her other philanthropic activities. There are also clippings and condolences on her death.
Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); Political campaigns -- United States; Prohibition; Government policy; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Religion; Philanthropy; Religious institutions; Travel; Rockefeller family -- Art collections; World War I; United States; Performing arts; Parks -- New York (State); New York (State); Medical research; Philanthropy -- United States; Charities; Charitable contributions; Arts
- Abby Rockefeller Mauzé - Family, 1
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents note
  Series 1, Family, contains documents on Abby Mauzé's husbands, David M. Milton, Dr. Irving H. Pardee, and Jean Mauzé. Most of the material documents the life of David Milton (11 folders), including correspondence he had with John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (1926-1957) on subjects ranging from travels to Christmas and birthday wishes. Of the eleven folders on David Milton, two are devoted to Equity Corporation, of which David Milton was President; these files contain mostly newspaper clippings and general correspondence. Two other folders contain materials on the Miltons' wedding (1925), including correspondence on wedding preparations, the invitation lists, and congratulatory letters.
  - Mauzé - General - Gifts, 1955-1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Newsy family letters. Gifts John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to Jean Mauzé.
  - Mauzé - Abby and Jean Mauzé Passports, 1953-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Milton - General Correspondence, 1925-1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Welcome into family. Business matters. Friendship with John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondents include David Milton, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Milton - Cabin at Pocantico, 1937-1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Built by David Milton, belonged to John D. Rockefeller Jr. Correspondents include David Milton, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Milton - Clips, 1965-1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Milton - Collateral from Abby Rockefeller Milton for Loan, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Abby Rockefeller Milton endorses Dave Milton notes at Chase bank. Correspondents include David Milton, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Milton - Divorce, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Clippings. Attorney's fees. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Robert W. Gumbel, Abby Rockefeller Mauzé.
  - Milton - Equity Corporation and Missouri Life Insurance Company, 1933-1957 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Financial history of Equity Corporation. Correspondents include David Milton, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Milton - Gifts and Loans, 1926-1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to David Milton.
  - Milton - Loan from Chase Bank Guaranteed by John D. Rockefeller, Jr., February 1940 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Loan made to buy Equity stock. Fully paid. Correspondents include David Milton, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Milton - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondence with Milton Family, 1934-1936 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Correspondents include David Milton, Abby Milton (O'Neill), and John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Milton - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondence with Milton Grandchildren, 1949, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Correspondents include Abby Milton O'Neill, George D. O'Neill, Marilyn Milton Simpson, and John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Milton - Rearrangement with Estate (Pocantico Hills) - Horses, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    David Milton's participation in farm activities. Correspondents include David Milton, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Milton - Wedding, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Engagement Publicity, letters of best wishes. Photographs, description of wedding and reception. Honeymoon. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. opens house to strangers after reception. Lists of those invited to reception. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Ivy Lee, Abby Rockefeller Milton.
  - Milton - Wedding Lists, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Pardee - Letters of Condolence, Clippings, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Pardee - Marriage, October 3, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Announcement of marriage to Dr. Irving H. Pardee. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Robert W. Gumbel, Abby Rockefeller Mauzé.
- Abby Rockefeller Mauzé - Finances, 2
  Series 2, Finances, includes two folders, "General" and "Correspondence," which contain information on some of Abby Mauzé's personal investments.
  The "Contributions" folder (1936-1961) is the only folder in the collection that contains material on Mrs. Mauzé's philanthropic activities. The material represented includes correspondence, memos, and lists (1941, 1959) on cash and stock contributions to East Woods School, The Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Rockefeller Brothers Fund, Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, New York Hospital, Y.W.C.A., Population Council, Planned Parenthood Federation of America, American Red Cross, Henry Street Settlement, and the purchase of copies of Raymond B. Fosdick's biography, "John D. Rockefeller, Jr.," to be given to libraries and newspapers. The folder also contains correspondence on donations to political organizations in support of the Republican Party (1936-1940).
  - General, 1907-1937 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Investments, advice. Summaries of income and taxes. Correspondents include Barton Turnbull, Bertram Cutler, Abby Rockefeller Mauzé, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - General, 1930-1937 (Box 2, Folder 18A)
  - American Founders Corporation Stock Transfer into Equity, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Small investment in David Milton's company. Corresponents include Barton Turnbull, Bertram Cutler, Abby Rockefeller Mauzé, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - American Founders Corporation Stock Transfer into Equity, 1934-1936 (Box 2, Folder 19A)
    Small investment in David Milton's company. Correspondents include Barton Turnbull, Bertram Cutler, Abby Rockefeller Mauzé, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Chase Bank Account, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Sale of Chase Stock, power of attorney. Correspondents include Barton Turnbull, Bertram Cutler, Abby Rockefeller Mauzé, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Contributions, 1936-1961 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Contributions made through office; some political, population control, and personal items. Not complete. Correspondents include Robert W. Gumbel, Dana S. Creel, Abby Rockefeller Mauzé.
  - Correspondence, 1937-1961 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Equitable Corporation Account - Chase National Bank, 1930-1934 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Investment service by bank. Correspondents include Barton Turnbull, Bertram Cutler, Abby Rockefeller Mauzé, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Equitable Corporation Account - Chase National Bank, 1930-1934 (Box 3, Folder 23A)
  - Income from Trust (John D. Rockefeller, Jr., December 1934 Trust), 1935-1938 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Correspondents include Barton Turnbull, Bertram Cutler, Abby Rockefeller Mauzé, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Loan Account, 1929, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. loan to buy apartment; later cancelled. Correspondents include Barton Turnbull, Bertram Cutler, Abby Rockefeller Mauzé, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Securities Purchased and Sales, 1907-1926 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    Office handled accounts. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Robert W. Gumbel, Abby Rockefeller Mauzé.
  - Statements of the Office Account, 1938-1943 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Payments by office, taxes, wages, gifts, miscellaneous. Correspondents include Barton Turnbull, Bertram Cutler, Abby Rockefeller Mauzé, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Trusts for Daughters, 1944-1960 (Box 6, Folder 67)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller, trustee with Chase Bank of December 1944 trust funds set up by Abby R. Mauzé for her two daughters (Abby R. Milton and Marilyn E. Milton). Management of trusts. Correspondents include Abby Rockefeller Mauzé, Bertram Cutler, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
  - Trust for Grandchildren, 1963-1966 (Box 6, Folder 67a)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted - Living Rockefeller family - Restricted for Live
  - Estate of Abby Rockefeller Mauzé - Tangible Personal Property (Box 6, Folder 68)
- Abby Rockefeller Mauzé - Real Estate, 3
  Series 3, Real Estate, consists of materials on the four properties that Abby Mauzé owned: a Bermuda property, Mill Neck House, property on the Pocantico Estate, and Roman Corporation - One Beekman Place. Of the thirteen folders in this subseries, seven are devoted to Pocantico Hills; two of these folders are closed. Most of the material concerning Pocantico includes property deeds, maps of the property, property assessments, and the payment of bills on work and inspections on the house.
  - Bermuda Property, 1935-1954 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    Purchase, sale of property. Correspondents include Abby Rockefeller Mauzé.
  - Mill Neck House - General, 1946-1958 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Care of House. Storm Damage. Correspondents include Robert W. Gumbel, Abby Rockefeller Mauzé.
  - Mill Neck House - Purchase, 1946-1956 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    Purchase of several parcels. Terms, closing statements. Correspondents include Robert W. Gumbel, Abby Rockefeller Mauzé.
  - Mill Neck House - Purchase of 5-Acre Tract, 1951-1952 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    Negotiations for Ryan 5 acre tract. Correspondents include Robert W. Gumbel, Abby Rockefeller Mauzé.
  - Mill Neck Property - 1958 Purchase (Box 3, Folder 32)
    Check transmittals. Correspondents include Robert W. Gumbel, Abby Rockefeller Mauzé.
  - Pocantico Hills - General, 1927-1946 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Pocantico Hills - Christmas Gift to Employees (Box 3, Folder 34)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Restricted - Confidential material.
  - Pocantico Hills - Estate Services Given to John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Children (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Pocantico Hills - Fuel Oil, 1939-1940 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Pocantico Hills Property, Gift - General Correspondence, 1937-1945 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave Abby Rockefeller Mauzé property for home at Pocantico Hills; assessments, sewer easement. Correspondents include Abby Rockefeller Mauzé, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Charles O. Heydt, Thomas M. Debevoise.
  - Pocantico Hills Property, Gift - Letters Re: Deed (Box 4, Folder 38)
    Total gift made in several parts. Correspondents include Abby Rockefeller Mauzé, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Charles O. Heydt, Thomas M. Debevoise.
  - Pocantico Hills House, 1938-1946 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    Plans, construction, valuation. Correspondents include David Milton, Thomas M. Debevoise, Robert W. Gumbel, Phillip Keebler.
  - Roman Corporation - One Beekman Place (Lease), 1934-1946 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    Ownership in cooperative apartment. Correspondents include Abby Rockefeller Mauzé, Robert W. Gumbel.
  - David Rockefeller Purchase of Pocantico Home (Hudson Pines), 1945-1946 (Box 6, Folder 69)
    Terms of Sale. Agreement. Finalized in May 1946.
- Abby Rockefeller Mauzé - Subject Files, 4
  Within Series 4, Subject Files, there are three folders of general correspondence (1905-1969). The bulk of the material in these folders consists of personal correspondence between Abby Rockefeller and her father, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (1914-1947), and outgoing correspondence from Robert W. Gumbel, Office Manager, who handled administrative affairs. (Gumbel's role was significant; his outgoing correspondence can be found in nearly every folder in the collection.) Other materials represented in the general correspondence folders include telegrams from John D. Rockefeller, Jr., her mother Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, and her five brothers; a music notebook (only one page is filled); and five letters of appeal from people Mrs. Mauzé did not know.
  The Subject Files also document birthday and Christmas gifts from John D. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (1924-1956); press and biographical material that includes partial transcripts of Abby Aldrich Rockefeller's letters to her sister, Lucy T. Aldrich, about Abby Mauzé (1919-1932); newspaper clippings and press releases on Abby Rockefeller as a debutante (1922) and on her subsequent marriages; and ticket, visa, and customs matters for domestic or overseas trips (1938, 1940-1943).
  - General Correspondence, 1905-1924 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    Scope and Contents
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gifts. Trips. Drawing by Sargent. Allowance. Debut. Speeding arrest. Marriage to Dave Milton, to Irving Pardee, to Jean Mauzé. Jewelry. Office matters. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Robert W. Gumbel, Abby Rockefeller Mauzé.
  - General Correspondence, 1925-1933 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - General Correspondence, 1934-1969 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Employees, 1935-1959 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    Hiring, insurance; sickness; accidents; salaries. Correspondents include Robert W. Gumbel, Abby Rockefeller Mauzé.
  - Employees, 1935-1959 (Box 4, Folder 44a)
    Restricted - Personnel - Open in 2027
  - Gifts, 1924-1956 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    From John D. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Robert W. Gumbel, Abby Rockefeller Mauzé.
  - Press (and Biographical) Material, 1919-1953 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Reception, November 1922 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    Mischa Elman played. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Robert W. Gumbel, Abby Rockefeller Mauzé.
  - Trips, 1940-1943 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    Railroad tickets only.
  - Trips - European Trip, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    Tickets, visas, customs.
- Abby Rockefeller Mauzé - Children and Grandchildren, 5
  Series 5 contains material regarding Abby Mauzé's children and grandchildren; the majority of this series is closed to researchers.
  - Abby Milton O'Neill - General, 1931-1950 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    Gifts, marriage, property, finances. Correspondents include Robert W. Gumbel, George D. O'Neill, Abby Milton O'Neill, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Abby Milton O'Neill - Purchase, Oyster Bay Property, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - George O'Neill - General, 1949-1959 (Box 5, Folder 52)
    4 items. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Abby Milton O'Neill - Contributions, 1950-1961 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Abby Milton O'Neill - Contributions, 1950-1961 (Box 5, Folder 53a)
    Conditions Governing Access Note
    Restricted - Living Rockefeller family - Restricted for Life
  - Abby Rockefeller O'Neill - Gifts, 1953-1960 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Catharine Mauzé O'Neill - General, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    Published newspaper clipping and press release of birth announcement of Catharine O'Neill.
  - Catharine Mauzé O'Neill - Gifts, 1958-1960 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - David Milton O'Neill - Gifts, 1955-1960 (Box 5, Folder 57)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gifts to David. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - George Dorr O'Neill, Jr. - General, 1950-1956 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - George Dorr O'Neill, Jr. - Gifts, 1951-1959 (Box 5, Folder 59)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gifts to George Jr. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Marilyn Milton Simpson - General, 1939-1960 (Box 5, Folder 60)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Marilyn's letters. School vacations, Europe, family marriages. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Marilyn Milton Simpson - Contributions, 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Marilyn Milton Simpson - Marriage, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Marilyn Milton Simpson - Gifts, 1932-1959 (Box 5, Folder 63)
    Gifts from John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - William Kelly Simpson - General, 1954-1955 (Box 5, Folder 64)
    3 items. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Abby Rockefeller Simpson - Gifts, 1958-1959 (Box 5, Folder 65)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gifts.
  - Laura Knickerbacker Simpson - Gifts, 1955-1959 (Box 5, Folder 66)
- Abby Rockefeller Mauzé - Personal Diaries, 6; 11 Bound Volumes
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  Series 6 consists of the personal diaries of Abby Rockefeller Mauzé.
  - Personal Diary, 1930, 1932-1934 (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - Personal Diary, 1935-1936 (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - Personal Diary, 1937-1938 (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - Personal Diary, 1947-1951, 1953-1954 (Box 7, Folder 73)
  - Personal Diary, 1954-1956 (Box 7, Folder 74)
  - Personal Diary, 1956-1958 (Box 7, Folder 75)
  - Personal Diary, 1959-1961 (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - Personal Diary, 1961-1964 (Box 8, Folder 77)
  - Personal Diary, 1965-1968 (Box 8, Folder 78)
  - Personal Diary, 1968-1971 (Box 8, Folder 79)
  - Personal Diary, 1971-1975 (Box 8, Folder 80)
- Abby Rockefeller Mauze family photographs, 1906-1983; 1005A; 133 prints
  Photographs
  - Prints
    - Abby Rockefeller Mauze family, 1906-1983; 30 prints (Box P 116)
    - Abby Milton O'Neill family, 1949-1950; 3 prints (Box P 116)
    - Group Portraits - Children, 1906-1947; 4 prints (Box P 161, Folder 1)
    - Marilyn Mauze Simpson, 1953; 7 prints (Box P 161, Folder 2)
    - Marilyn Mauze Simpson family - Laura Simpson, 1 print (Box P 161, Folder 3)
    - David Merriwether Milton, Jr., 3 prints (Box P 161, Folder 4)
    - Abby Rockefeller Milton - Wedding, 1925; 9 prints (Box P 161, Folder 5)
    - Abby Rockefeller Milton O'Neill, 1949; 2 prints (Box P 161, Folder 6)
    - George O'Neill, 1 print (Box P 161, Folder 7)
    - Abby Rockefeller Mauze - Philanthropies - Greenacre Foundation - Vest Pocket Park, 1969; 5 prints (Box P 161, Folder 8)
    - Abby Rockefeller Mauze - Portraits, 36 prints (Box P 161, Folder 9)
  - Albums
    - Greenacre Park Foundation, 1972; 23 prints (Box A 44)
  - Oversized
    - Abby Rockefeller Mauze family, 1925-1967; 3 prints (Box O 14)
    - Abby Rockefeller Mauze family, 6 prints (Box O 36)
    - Newspaper article-oversized, "Abby Rockefeller is stepping on the gas again", 1924 September 7; PUBLICATION (Quantity 1) (Folder 1, Folder 84)